Özge Nilay Yalçın, PhD

sfu.ca/~oyalcin github.com/onyalcin Vancouver, BC, Canada +1 (604) 367 1299 n.y.ozge@gmail.com

SUMMARY

I am a Postdoctoral Researcher at Simon Fraser University, with a research focusing on modeling empathy in 3D virtual agents. During my PhD work, I was responsible for implementing the architecture for a real-time conversational system with speech and non-verbal emotional behaviors that are automatically generated. I am highly self-motivated and can work without supervision to plan, initiate and realize projects to develop systems and research from start to finish. I am interested in contributing to the field through open-source and share my ideas. I have been combining my backgrounds in Management Engineering and Cognitive Science to build and lead an interdisciplinary group of researchers, directing and mentoring undergraduate and graduate students at Simon Fraser University.

SPECIALITIES

- Conducting research starting with establishing theoretical foundations to modeling, designing experiments, data collection, data analysis and publishing
- Working and communicating ideas with interdisciplinary teams
- Leading and mentoring research groups
- Developing and applying statistical modeling and machine learning techniques
- Development of architectures based on human cognitive processes

INTERESTS

- Affective Computing
- Cognitive Modeling
- Human-Computer Interaction
- Embodied Conversational Agents

- Computational Models
- Natural Language Processing (NLP)
- Data Science
- Al Ethics

SKILLS

Technical Skills

- Python, Bash
- NLTK, SciPy, Pandas, Matplotlib
- TensorFlow, Keras, Torch, Theano, Caffe
- OpenCV, PvAudio, CMU Sphinx
- Google Cloud APIs, IBM Watson, AWS, DialogueFlow
- SPSS, R, Tableau, JMP
- Git
- Latex

Toolsets

- Amazon MTurk, PsiTurk, JsPsych
- Experiment Builder, OpenSesame
- USC Smartbody
- ACT-R
- Tobii Studio, Eye-tracker, Tobii Glasses
- Eyelink 1000
- Microsoft Kinect
- Emotiv Epoc+ EEG Headset
- Unity

EDUCATION

Simon Fraser University, Vancouver, Canada

PhD in Interactive Arts and Technology

Fall 2015 GPA: 4.00/4.00

Middle East Technical University, Ankara, Turkey

MSc in Cognitive Science Graduated with Honors

GPA: 4.00/4.00

Istanbul Technical University, Istanbul, Turkey

Bachelor's Degree in Management Engineering

Entering 4th in the faculty

GPA: 2.57/4.00

September 2015 - 2019

February 2012 - September 2014

October 2005 - June 2010

Developing Interactive 3D Virtual Agents

2016-current

Affective Virtual Human group at iVizLab, Simon Fraser University Leading and mentoring an interdisciplinary research group

- Unity Character group:
 - Leading design students to model realistic 3D virtual characters
 - Leading gesture generation group for body and facial gestures
- Leading the computer science students for developing behavior synchronization system for Behaviour Mark-up Language (BML) notation
- · Smartbody group:
 - Leading design students for environment (lighting, scene)
 - Leading gesture generation group for new body and facial gestures
- Health Applications Group
 - Leading developers for extending the M-PATH system (see below) with command-based interaction functionality
 - Leading content generation process for extending the dialogue system of M-PATH

Modeling Empathy in Embodied Conversational Agents

2016-2019

PhD Thesis, Simon Fraser University

Developed a framework for 3D Virtual Agents with empathy behavior, including real-time conversational abilities with multimodal emotion recognition and expression behavior Contributions:

- Designing and developing the innovative cognitive architecture M-PATH
- Facial emotion recognition (OpenCV Haar Cascade for face detection, CNN on Keras with Tensorflow backend, trained on CK+ dataset)
- Speech Recognition (Google Cloud Speech API with streaming input)
- Voice emotion recognition (librosa to extract MFCC features, CNN on Keras with Tensorflow backend, trained on RAVDESS dataset)
- Sentiment Analysis (Modified Vader and SO-CAL sentiment analyzers with NRC Emotion Lexicons for word-level/sentence-level emotion recognition and sentiment analysis)
- Dialogue Manager (Used python NLTK and sklearnIncluding TF-idf, intent/context classification for QA with topic hierarchy, Survey Manager and response classification with fine-tuned BERT with pytorch)
- Behavior Controller system that controls conversational turn-taking and decisions on empathic behavior (mimicry, affect matching, emotion regulation) based on system goals, user model and history of the interaction
- Automated real-time behavior generation for synchronized gestures with speech for 3D Virtual Agent. Generating emotional and personality-based behavior with BML notation to be consumed by the Smartbody or Unity character animation platforms.
- Planning, designing and conducting experiments using the system in real-time and Amazon MTurk. Analysing the data and dissemination of the results in academic journals and venues.

Al-generated Anonymization in VR Journalism

2017-2019

Research Assistant, Simon Fraser University

2017-18 Knight Foundation / Google News Lab / Online News Association Journalism Grant Developed computational abstraction techniques to generate videos and images that will best convey the emotional information

Contributions:

- Video segmentation using saliency models in Caffe
- Style transfer and abstraction of the images using Painterly model
- Development of interactive system using Kinect and movement analysis
- Planning, designing and conducting experiments using the system in real-time and Amazon MTurk. Analysing the data and dissemination of the results in academic journals and venues.

Eye tracking patterns for development of object and face expertise

2016-2017

Research Assistant, Simon Fraser University

Comparison of attention and search behavior of children with autism spectrum disorder Contributions:

- Designing the experimental setup on EyeLink equipment using Experiment Builder in Python
- Evaluating the collected data with pandas, scipy and matplotlib

Error Recovery in Speech Recognition Systems

2015-2016

Research Assistant, Simon Fraser University

Investigating the sources of error in speech recognizers and build efficient systems for error recovery

Contributions:

- UI design for error recovery list-based system using kivy in Python
- Setting up speech recognizer using CMU Sphinx

Investigation of Cognitive Processes in Reading

2014-2015

Research Assistant, Middle East Technical University

Developing a corpus of Turkish reading patterns, consisting of fixation location, duration and saccadic amplitude information for both silent and oral reading using eye-tracking Contributions:

- Preparation of a corpora of words and sentences to be used in the experiment, based on their frequency of use and grammatical properties
- Experimental data collection using Eye-Tracking equipment
- Modeling the reading patterns in Turkish reading process with Linear Mixed Models and Statistical Methods by using the collected data
- Dissemination of the results in academic venues

Modeling and Predicting the Effect of Culture in Communication:

2013-2014

A Mixed Study Using Naming Game and Social Networks

MSc Thesis, Middle East Technical University

Using multi-agent simulation of a variation of Naming Game with social links to model information diffusion in social platforms

Contributions:

- Mining Twitter data based on hashtag use on popular political topics
- Cleaning and anonymizing the collected data
- Analyzing and modeling the change in the usage of hashtags using Naming Game paradigm, based on social network analysis in Gephi
- · Visualization of the simulation using NetworkX

Automatic Song Tagging and Recommendation System

2013

Middle East Technical University

Classifying music data according to mood and genre by using supervised learning to be used in recommendation systems

Contribution:

- Data collection, cleaning, sampling and annotation
- Applying Audio Feature Extraction methods to extract low-level features from audio samples
- Clustering the samples in Weka with kNN
- · Recommendation system via calculating similarity based on mood and genre

EMPLOYMENT

Simon Fraser University, Surrey, Canada Postdoctoral Researcher at iVizLab Simon Fraser University, Surrey, Canada Sep 2019 - current

Sep 2016 - 2019

Research Assistant under supervision of Prof. Dr. Steve DiPaola Simon Fraser University, Surrey, Canada Teaching Assistant of Introduction to Cognitive Science course	Sep 2016 - 2017
Instructor Jeremy Turner	.
	Sep 2015 - Sep 2016
Research Assistant under supervision of Prof. Dr. Wolfgang Stuerzlinger Middle East Technical University, Ankara, Turkey Research Assistant under the supervision of Assist. Dr. Cengiz Acartürk	Oct 2014 - 2015
Received full Tübitak Scholarship	
Botègo, Yapayzeki Yazılım Ltd. Şti., Istanbul, Turkey	Aug-Sep 2009
Intern	
 Developing intelligent virtual assistants for company websites 	
Continental Mechanical Components GmbH, Roding, Germany	Jul-Aug 2008
Intern	
 Involved in two R&D projects and quality assurance of diesel pumps 	

ACADEMIC SERVICE AND MEMBERSHIPS

Association for Computing Machinery (ACM) SIGCHI & ACM-W Membership	2018 - current
Women in Machine Learning (WiML) Membership	2019 - current
Women in Computing Science Member and Mentor at SFU	2019 - current
Organizing Committee of Biologically Inspired Cognitive Architectures Conference (BIC	(A) 2019
Cognitive Science Society Student Member	2018 - 2019
SFU Graduate Student Society Councillor	2017 - 2019